<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A collection of all the statutes now in force, against the transportation of woll, &amp;c. with notes in the margin</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Laws, statutes, etc.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09009</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64551215</idno>
  <idno type="VID">184548</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240860653</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E882A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R176054</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">64551215</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09009)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2866:46)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A collection of all the statutes now in force, against the transportation of woll, &amp;c. with notes in the margin</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Laws, statutes, etc.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>77, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Bill and the Executrix of Thomas Newcomb deceas'd, Printers to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages are cropped.</note>
                  <note>Royal arms on title page.</note>
                  <note>Includes five pages of manuscript notes at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Woolen goods industry --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Hides and skins industry --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Law --  England --  Digests --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:2"/>
            <p>A COLLECTION Of all the STATUTES Now in FORCE, Against the Transportation of Wooll, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>With NOTES in the Margin.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>HON SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
               <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Charles Bill,</hi> and the Executrix of <hi>Thomas Newcomb</hi> deceas'd, Printers to the Kings most Excellent Majesty. 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:184548:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anno XII. CAROLI II. Regis.</hi> An Act for Prohibiting the Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Wooll, Woolfels, Fullers Earth, or any kind of Scouring Earth.</head>
            <p>FOR the better preventing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding of such losses and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies as have happened, and daily do and may happen to the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and to the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by and through the secret and subtil Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation and Transportation, and by and through the secret and subtil carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and conveying away of Wooll, Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn, made of Wooll, Wool-flocks, Fullers Earth, and Fulling Clay, out of, and from the Kingdoms and Dominion afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, and for the better setting on work the poor people and Inhabitants of the Kingdoms and Dominion aforesaid; And to the intent that the full and best use and benefit of the principal native Commodities of the same Kingdoms and Dominion may come, redound, and be unto and amongst the Subjects and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184548:4"/> of the same, and not unto or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Subjects and Inhabitants of the Realm of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or of any Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Realms or States, as the same now of late in some great Measure hath done, and is further likely to do, if some severer punishment than here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore be not speedily inflicted upon such offenders as shall be actors or asi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in and to such exportation and transportation, and in and to such carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and conveying away thereof, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid;</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No person after the 14 of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi> 1660. shall exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sheep or Wool, Woolfels. Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn, Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flocks, Fullers-earth, or Fulling-clay.</note>Be it enacted by the Kings most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majesty, the Lords and Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, That no person or persons whatsoever, from and after the fourteenth day of <hi>January,</hi> One thousand six hundred and threescore, shall directly or indirectly export, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, carry or convey, or cause or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to be exported, transported, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or conveyed, out of, or from the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> or out of, or from the Isles of <hi>Jersey</hi> or <hi>Guernsey,</hi> with <hi>Sarke</hi> and <hi>Alderney,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the Government of <hi>Guernsey</hi> aforesaid, or out of, or from any of them, or out of, or from the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> aforesaid, into any parts or places out of the Kingdoms, Isles or Dominion aforesaid, any Sheep or Wooll whatsoever, of the breed or growth of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> or Isles, or Dominion aforesaid; Or any Woolfels, Mortlings, or Shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, or any Yarn made of Wooll, or any Woolflocks, or any Fullers-earth, or Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-Clay
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184548:4"/> whatsoever; Nor shall direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or indirectly pack or load,<note place="margin">Nor car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, load, or board any Sheep, Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> or cause to be packed or loaded upon any Horse, Car or other Carriage, or load or lay on board, or cause to be loaden or laid on board in any Ship or other Vessel, in any Place or Port within the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> or Isles, or Dominion aforesaid, any such Sheep, Wooll, Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll or Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flocks, or any Fullers-earth, or Fulling-clay to the intent or purpose to export, transport, carry or convey the same, or to cause the same to be exported, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported carried or conveyed out of the Kingdoms of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> Isles or Dominion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, or with intent or purpose that any other person or persons should so export, transport, carry or convey the same into any parts or places out of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> Isles or Dominion aforesaid, into the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> or any foreign parts.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authority aforesaid, That no Wooll,<note place="margin">No Wooll Woolfels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> after the 14 of <hi>January,</hi> 1660. to be carried out of <hi>Wales, Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of wooll, woolflocks, or any Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers-earth, or Fulling clay, shall be from and after the Fourteenth day of <hi>January,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hundred and sixty, exported, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, carried or conveyed out of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> or Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> or out of any Port or Place of the said Kingdoms respectively, unto the Isles of <hi>Jersey</hi> or <hi>Guernsey,</hi> or to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184548:5"/>
               <hi>Sarke,</hi> or <hi>Alderney</hi> except as in this Act shall hereafter be limited or appointed.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid,<note place="margin">The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties.</note> That all and every the Offender and Offenders, Offence and Offences aforesaid, shall be subject and liable to the respective pains, penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and forfeitures hereafter following, That is to say, The said Sheep, Wooll, Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Woolflocks, Fullers-earth, and Fulling-Clay so exported, transported, carried, conveyed, packed or loaden contrary to the true intent of this Act, shall be forfeited, and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very offender and offenders therein shall forfeit Twenty Shillings for every such Sheep, and Three Shillings for every pound weight of such Wooll, Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Woolflocks, Fullers-earth, or Fulling-clay; And also the Owners of the said Ships or Vessels knowing such Offence, shall forfeit all their interest in the said Ships or Vessels, with all their Apparel and Furniture to them and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of them belonging; And that the Master and Mariners thereof, knowing such Offence, and wittingly and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aiding and assisting thereunto, shall forfeit all their Goods and Chattels, and have imprisonment for the space of Three months without Bail or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise; the one moiety of which said penalties and forfeitures shall be to the Kings Majesty, his Heirs and Successors, and the other moiety to him that will sue for the same by Action of Debt, Bill, Plaint or Information in any of his Majesties Courts of Record, or before
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184548:5"/> the Justices of Assize, or in the general Quarter Sessions of the Peace: In which suit no essoin, protection or wager of Law shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted That if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Merchant,<note place="margin">The pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty upon any Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant that shall trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> or other person or persons shall after the said fourteenth day of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> transport or cause to be transport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any Sheep, Wooll, Woolfels, Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Shorlings, Woollen-yarn, Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flocks, Fullers earth or Fulling-clay, contrary to the true intent of this Act, and be thereof lawfully Convicted, That then he shall be disabled to require any Debt or Accompt of any Factor or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for or concerning any Debt or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state properly belonging to such Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Provided always,<note place="margin">Proviso.</note> and it is never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless declared, That this Act, or any thing therein Contained, shall not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strued to take away any greater pains or penalties inflicted, or to be inflicted for any the offences aforesaid, by virtue of any former Act of Parliament now in force.</p>
            <p>And be it also further enacted by the authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Offences against this Act where to be tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> That every offence that shall be done or committed contrary to this Act, shall and may be enquired of, and heard, examined, tried, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in the County where such Sheep, Wooll, Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Woolflocks, Fullers-earth, or Fulling clay respectively shall be so packed, loaden, or laid aboard, as aforesaid, contrary to this Act, or else in the County where such Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders shall happen to be apprehended or arrested for such offence, in such man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and form, and to such effect to all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184548:6"/> intents and purposes, as if the same of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence had been wholly and altogether done and committed at and in such County.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it enacted by the authority aforesaid, That no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons whatsoever,<note place="margin">They to be prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted within a year after the offence commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> shall at any time hereafter be impeached for any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence aforesaid, unless such person or persons shall be prosecuted within the space of one year next ensuing such of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That it shall and may be lawful to and for any person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to seize,<note place="margin">Any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son may seize goods loaded contrary to this Act with intent to be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and shall have the moiety thereof.</note> take and challenge to his or their own use and behoof, and to the use of the King, his Heirs and Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, all and all manner such Sheep, Wooll, Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Woolflocks, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers-earth, and Fulling-clay, as he or they shall happen to see, find, know or discover to be laid aboard in any Ship or other Vessel or Boat, or to be brought, carried or laid on shore, at or near the Sea, or any Navigable River or Water, to the intent or purpose to be exported or conveyed out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> Isles or Dominion afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, contrary to the true meaning of this Act, or to be packed or loaden upon any Horse, Cart or other Carriage, to the intent or purpose to be conveyed or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, and that such person or persons as shall happen so to seize, take or chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge any such Sheep, Wooll, Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184548:6"/> Wooll, Wool-flocks, Fullers-earth, or Fulling-clay, as aforesaid, shall have the full moiety thereof to all intents and purposes.</p>
            <p>Provided always,<note place="margin">Proviso, such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son shall not be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the offender.</note> That such person or persons as shall make any such seizure or challenge, as aforesaid, to his or their own use, shall not be admitted or allowed to give in Evidence upon his or their Oath or Oaths against any person or persons which shall happen to be indicted, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused or questioned by virtue of this Act, or any thing therein contained.</p>
            <p>And furthermore be it enacted by the authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Forfeiture of the Ship, if the Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be an Alien, or not inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting in <hi>England</hi>
               </note> That all and every Ship, Vessel, Hulk, Barge or Boat, of what kind soever, whereof any Alien born, or whereof any natural born Subjects not inhabiting within the Realm of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> shall be Owner or part Owner, and wherein any Sheep, Wooll, Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Woolflocks, Fullers earth, or Fulling-clay, shall happen to be ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, put, or laid aboard contrary to the true meaning of this Act, shall be forfeited to the Kings Majesty, His Heirs and Successors.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That this Act shall not extend, to any Lamb-Skins ready drest, and prepared fit and useful for Furr or Linings.</p>
            <p>Provided also,<note place="margin">Proviso</note> That this Act shall not in any wise extend to the transporting carrying or conveying away of any such woolfels or Pelts, with such Wooll upon them, or to any Beds stuffed with Flocks, which shall be carried or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in any Ship or other Vessel for neccessary use only, of and about the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184548:7"/> Ordnance or other thing in or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning such Ship or Vessel, or only for the necessary use of any the persons in such Ship or Vessel passing or being, and which shall not be sold or uttered in any Foreign parts out of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">England, Ireland, Berwick.</note> or Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> Isles or Dominion aforesaid; nor to the exporting, transporting, carrying or conveying of any Wether Sheep, or of the Wooll growing upon any such Wether Sheep, to be carried alive in any Ship or other Vessel, for and towards the only necessary Food or Diet of or for the Company or Passengers, or other persons therein, and for and towards none other purpose.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it further enacted,<note place="margin">Proviso.</note> That this Act, or any thing therein contained, shall not extend to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such Wooll to be exported or trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported out of, or from the Port of <hi>Southampton</hi> only,<note place="margin">Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey, Guern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey.</note> unto the aforesaid Isles of <hi>Jersey</hi> and <hi>Guernsey,</hi> by, or for the only use or behoof of any of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the said Isles of <hi>Jersey</hi> or <hi>Guernsey,</hi> or either of them, or to any such Wooll to be shipped or loaden a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board in any Ship or other Vessel, by, or for the only use or behoof of any the Inhabitants of the said Isles of <hi>Jersey</hi> and <hi>Guernsey,</hi> or either of them, in the Port aforesaid, to be exported and transported into the said Isles of <hi>Jersey</hi> or <hi>Guernsey,</hi> or either of them; so as such person or persons that shall so ship or lay aboard such Wooll into any Ship or other Vessel, do before the ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or laying aboard such Wooll, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver unto the Customer, Comptroller,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184548:7"/> Surveyor, or Searcher of the Port of <hi>Southampton</hi> aforesaid (out of which the same Wooll is to be exported) a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting under the Seal or Seals of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Governors of the same Isles of <hi>Guernsey</hi> or <hi>Jersey,</hi> unto which the said Wooll is to be transported, or of his or their Deputy or Deputies respectively, the which writing shall purport and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press that the party named in such wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is authorised and appointed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port or cause to be exported out of the Port aforesaid, so much Wooll, expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the number of the Tods, to the same Isle, to be used or manufactured in one of the same Isles, or in some of the members or parts of the same, and that such party so authorised and appointed to export, or cause to be exported that Wooll, hath before the making and sealing of that writing, entred into sufficient Bond to his Majesties use for the landing of the said wooll in that Isle. And to the intent that the quantity of Wooll to be exported out of the Port of <hi>Southampton</hi> aforesaid into the said Isles, or either of them, in any one year, accompting the year to begin from the first day of <hi>January</hi> next ensuing, and so yearly from the first day of <hi>Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> may not exceed the quantity here under specified, that is to say, unto the Isle of <hi>Jersey,</hi> Two thousand Tods and no more of unkeamed Wooll, and unto <hi>Guernsey,</hi> One thousand Tods and no more of unkeamed Wooll, and unto <hi>Alderney,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alderney, Sark.</note> Two hundred Tods and no more of unkeamed Wooll, and unto <hi>Sark,</hi> One hundred Tods of unkeamed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184548:8"/> Wooll and no more, every Tod not exceeding Thirty two Pounds.</p>
            <p>And be it enacted by the authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, That the Governour of the said Isle of <hi>Jersey,</hi> or his Deputy, for whom he will answer, shall not make to any person or persons, any writing or writings such as is above specified, to authorise or appoint such person or persons, as aforesaid, to fetch, export or transport out of the Port of <hi>Southam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton</hi> aforesaid, unto the said Isle of <hi>Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey,</hi> in one year, accounting the year from the first day of <hi>January,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand six hundred and sixty aforesaid, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny greater quantity of Wooll than Two thousand Tods in any one year, and the Governour of the said Isle of <hi>Guernsey,</hi> or his Deputy, for whom he will answer, shall not make to any person or persons, any writing or writings, such as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove specified, to authorise and appoint such person or persons, as aforesaid, to fetch, export or transport out of the port above specified, unto the said Isles of <hi>Guernsey,</hi> with <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derney,</hi> and <hi>Sark,</hi> in any one year, accounting the year from the first day of <hi>January,</hi> any greater quantity of Wooll than One thousand Tods for <hi>Guernsey,</hi> Two hundred Tods for <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derney,</hi> and One hundred Tods for <hi>Sark,</hi> in any one year; and that the Customer of the Port of <hi>Southampton</hi> aforesaid, shall keep a true account of all the said quantity of Woolls so by him permitted to be loaden by virtue of this Act, and shall not permit any greater quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Woolls to be loaden than by this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184548:8"/> Act is prescribed, in any one year, to either of the said Islands respectively, under any pretence whatsoever, upon the penalty of the forfeiture of his place, and the sum of One hundred Pounds in money to him or them that will Sue for the same in any Court of Record, wherein no Essoin, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection or Wager of Law shall be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And if any of the Governours afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, or any of their, or either of their Deputy or Deputies of the said Isles, or either of them, shall give, grant, or make any Licence or Licences for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting from <hi>Southampton</hi> aforesaid, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the said Isles respectively, of any greater quantity of such Wooll than is before by the true meaning of this Act limited and appointed in that behalf; That then the respective Governour or Governours of such of the said Isles shall forfeit and pay to the Kings Majesty, His Heirs and Successors, the sum of Twenty pounds of lawful Money of <hi>England,</hi> for every Tod of Wooll which shall be so licensed to be exported, over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the rate and proportion of Wooll in and by this Act, or the true meaning thereof, limited or appointed.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That the respective Governours aforesaid, or their respective Deputies, or any of their Clerks, Officers or Servants, for the granting, making or sealing of every such writing of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence as is aforesaid, and for the entring a Remembrance of the same into some Book, which they shall have and keep for that purpose, may have and take the sum of Twelve pence and no more, upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184548:9"/> pain of forfeiting to the party grieved the sum of Five Shillings for every Peny which shall be taken over and above the said sum of Twelve Pence in and by this Act allowed to be taken, and so after that proportion; the said penalty or forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the taking above Twelve Pence as aforesaid, to be recovered by Bill, Plaint, or Information, in any Court of Record at <hi>Westminster,</hi> or elsewhere, wherein no injunction, protection, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, essoin or wager of law shall be admitted or allowed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:184548:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anno XIV. CAROLI II. Regis.</hi> An Act against the Exporting of Sheep, Wooll, Woolfels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wooll-flocks, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Earth, Fulling-clay, and Tobacco-pipe-clay.</head>
            <p>WHereas against the Laws of this Kingdom, great numbers of Sheep, and great quantities of Wooll, Wool-fels. Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wool-flocks, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers-earth, or Fulling-clay are secretly exported, transported, carried and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed out of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> the Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> into the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and into foreign parts to the great decay of the Woollen Manufactures, the ruine of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Families, and the destruction of the Navigation and Commerce of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Town and Dominion aforesaid, which is like daily to increase if some further remedy be not provided, and further penalties imposed upon the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders therein:</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:184548:10"/>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by the Kings most excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, That if any person or persons shall from and after the first day of <hi>August,</hi> One thousand six hundred sixty and two,<note place="margin">Exporting or carrying of Sheep, Wooll, Wool-fels, Mortling, Shorlings, Yarn, Wool-flocks, Fullers-earth, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-clay, out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Wales, or Ireland.</hi>
               </note> directly or indirectly, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, transport, carry or convey, or shall cause to be exported, transported, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or conveyed out of, or from the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the first day of <hi>January,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand six hundred sixty and two, out of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> into any parts or places out of the Kingdoms, or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion aforesaid, or into the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> any Sheep or Wooll whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of the breed or growth of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms or Dominion aforesaid, or any Wool-fels Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wool, Wool-flocks, or any Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers-earth, or Fulling-clay whatsoever, or shall directly or indirectly pack or load, or cause to be packed or loaden, upon any Horse, Cart or other Carriage, or shall load or lay on board, or cause to be loaden or laid on board, in any Ship or other Vessel, in any place within the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed</hi> aforesaid, any such Sheep, Wooll, Wool-fels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wool-flock, Fullers-earth, or Fulling-clay, to the intent or purpose, to export, transport, carry or convey the same, or to cause the same to be exported, transported, carried or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184548:10"/> out of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, into the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or into any foreign parts, that then every such offence shall be adjudged Felony,<note place="margin">Made Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony.</note> and the offender or offenders being duly convicted, shall suffer and forfeit as in case of Felony.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Aiders and Assisters therein shall be adjudged Felons.</note> That every Owner of any such Ship or other Vessel, and every Owner of every Horse, Cart or Carriage, upon which any Sheep, Wooll, Wool-fels, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wool-flocks, Fullers-earth or Fulling-clay, shall be so exported, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, carried or conveyed, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, or to any such intent or purpose, as aforesaid, knowing thereof, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wittingly and willingly aiding, assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or consenting thereunto, and also eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Master and Mariner of or in such Ship or other Vessel, wherein any such Sheep, Wooll, Wool-fels, Mortlings, Shorlings Yarn made of Wooll, Wool-flocks, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers-earth or fulling-clay, shall be so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, transported, carried or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed, or loaden or laid on Board, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, to any such intent or purpose, as aforesaid, knowing thereof, and being wittingly and willingly aiding, assisting or consenting thereunto, and also eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Factor or Servant, or other person whatsoever, and every Customer, Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troller, Waiter, Searcher, Surveyor, or other Officer, or person whatsoever, knowing thereof, and being wittingly or willingly aiding, assisting or consenting thereunto, shall be, and shall be adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184548:11"/> and taken to be a Felon, and every offender or offenders therein being duly convicted, shall suffer and forfeit as in case of Felony.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Offences against this Act, where to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and tried.</note>And be it further enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid. That every offence which shall be done or committed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this Act, shall and may be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, and heard, examined, tried and determined in the County where such Sheep, Wooll, Wool-fels, Mortlings, Shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wool-flocks, Fullers-earth or Fulling-clay respective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shall be so packed, laiden or lade on Board, as aforesaid, or else in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty where such offender shall happen to be apprehended or arrested for such of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, in such manner and form, and to such effect, to all intents and purposes as if the same offence had been wholly done and committed in the same County.</p>
            <p>Provided also, That every Baron, and other Peer of this Realm, which shall be indicted or accused as principal, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary in or to any offence made Felony by this Act, shall have his, her or their Trial, by his, her or their Peers<note place="margin">Peers.</note> as in case of Felony, at the Common Law.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">None to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached, unless within one Year next after the Offence commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>Provided always, and be it enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That no person or persons whatsoever, shall at any time hereafter be impeached for any offence made Felony by this Act, unless such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons shall be thereof indicted within the space of one year next ensuing such offence committed.</p>
            <p>And forasmuch as great quantities of Wooll, Woollen-Yarn, and Wool-flocks, are close packed and pressed together with Scrues, and other unlawful Engines,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184548:11"/> into Buts, Pipes, Hogsheads, Chests and other Casks and Vessels, and into Sacks, Baggs, and other wrappers made of Wooll or Linen, and under colour of Bales, Sacks, Baggs, Packs and Casks of other Goods, and otherwise, great quantities of the same are daily loaden on Board of Ships or other Vessels, and so are carried, conveyed, exported, and transported out of the Kingdoms, Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> and Dominion aforesaid; and also great quantities are daily car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and laid at, or near the Coasts of the Sea or some Navigable Rivers, into Store-houses and Barns, and by night are laid on Board of Shallops, and other Vessels belonging to Aliens, and so carried and exported out of the Kingd ms, Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> and Dominion aforesaid:<note place="margin">Scrues and unlawful Engines for pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Wooll, not to be used.</note> Be it therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority aforesaid, That from and after the first day of <hi>August,</hi> no person or persons shall press together with any Scrues, Presses or other Engines, into any Sack, Pack, Bagg or other Wrapper, or shall put, press, pack or stean any Wooll whatsoever, or any Yarn made of Wooll, into any Butt, Pipe, Hogshead, Chest or any other Cask or Vessel, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any pretence whatsover, or shall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or lay, or cause to be carried or laid at or near the Shore or Coasts of the Sea, or of any Navigable River, or into any house or place near adjoyning thereunto, any such Wooll, woolflocks, or Yarn made of Wooll, with intention to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, transport, carry or convey the same out of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> into the Kingdom of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184548:12"/>
               <hi>Scotland,</hi> or unto any foreign parts, under the penalty<note place="margin">The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> of the loss and forfeiture of all such Wooll, Wool-flocks and Yarn made of Wooll, as shall be so packed or pressed, or put or laid into Cask, or carried or laid near to the Sea-Shore, or to any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigable River as aforesaid, or the value thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fulling clay, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco-pipe-clay, not to be exported.</note>And whereas great quantities of Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers earth or Fulling-clay are daily car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and exported under the colour of Tobacco-pipe-clay: Be it therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the authority aforesaid, That no Tobacco-pipe-clay shall from and after the First day of <hi>August,</hi> One thousand six hundred sixty and two, be exported, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, carried or conveyed out of, or from the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed;</hi> or after the first day of <hi>January,</hi> One thousand six hundred sixty and two, out of or from the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> into the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or into any foreign parts, or into any Port or Place out of the Kingdom or Dominion afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, under the penalty<note place="margin">The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> of Three shillings for every pound of Tobacco-pipe-clay which shall be exported or transported contrary to this Act.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Packs of Wooll, Wool-fels <hi>&amp;c.</hi> shall not be carried but in the day time.</note>And be it further enacted, by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That from and after the first day of <hi>August,</hi> One thousand six hundred sixty and two, no Packs, Sacks, Baggs or Cask of any Wooll, Wool-fels Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wool-flocks, Fullers-earth, Fulling-clay, or Tobacco-pipe-clay, shall be laid or loaded on any Horse, Cart, or other Carriage what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, or shall be carried or conveyed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184548:12"/> by land to or from any place or places within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> or Dominion aforesaid, nor after the first day of <hi>January,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand six hundred sixty two, in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but in the day time, and at seasonable hours (that is to say,) from and after the first day of <hi>March,</hi> to the nine and twentieth day of <hi>September</hi> yearly, between the hours of four of the Clock in the morning, and eight of the Clock in the evening, and from the nine and twentieth day of <hi>September,</hi> to the first day of <hi>March,</hi> yearly, between the hours of seven of the Clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and five of the Clock in the evening, under the penalty<note place="margin">the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> of the loss and forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all such Goods, or the value there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; the one moiety of all which Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures mentioned in this Act, to be to the use of the King, his Heirs and Successors and the other moiety to him or them that will sue for the same by Action of Debt, Bill, Plaint or Information in any Court of Record, in which no Essoin, Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Wager of Law shall be admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>Provided nevertheless, That this Act,<note place="margin">Proviso concerning The Act.</note> or any thing therein contained, shall not extend, or be construed to extend to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal Disanul and make Void, any the Penalties, Clauses, or Provisoes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in one Act of this present Session of Parliament, made against the transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of wooll, Wool-fels, Fullers-earth, or any kind of scouring Earth, or to the Prohibiting of the loading on Board any Ship or Vessel, of any Wether-sheep, Wooll, Wool-flocks or other Goods mentioned in this Act, that by the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:184548:13"/> aforesaid Act is permitted to be loaden on Board of any Ship or Vessel, for the necessary Use and Provision of such Ship or Vessel, as aforesaid; any thing in this Act contained to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Proviso for Owners of Ships that have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and shall first disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the same.</note>Provided always, That if any Owner of any Ship or Vessel, or any Master or Mariner knowing of such transportation of such Sheep, Wooll, Wool-fels, Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wool-flocks, Fullers-earth Fulling-clay, or Tobacco-pipe-clay, shall within three months next after the knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or after his return into the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi> or into the said Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> aforesaid, give the first information <hi>bona fide,</hi> before any of the Barons of either of the Courts of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the time being, or before the head Officer of any Port where he shall first arrive, upon his or their Oath, of the number and quantity of the Goods mentioned in this Act, so carried, conveyed and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and by whom, where and in what Ship or Vessel, and afterwards shall be ready upon reasonable warning by Process to justifie and prove the same, That then such Owner and Owners, Master, Mariner and Mariners shall not be punished for Felony by virtue of this Act, but shall nevertheless be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, to all other Penalties and Forfeitures in this or any other Act contained, for the Offence aforesaid; and all such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, transportation, carrying or conveying of any the Goods,<note place="margin">Common Nusance.</note> Wares or Commodities in this Act mentioned, is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184548:13"/> hereby declared and adjudged to be a Common and publick Nusance.</p>
            <p>And for the better execution of this Act, Be it further enacted,<note place="margin">Who may hear and determine the same Offences.</note> That all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices of Assize, Justices of Goal-delivery, and Justices of Peace, shall enquire of all the Premisses in their General Quarter-Sessions, and hear and determine the same; and that all Mayors, Bailiffs, and other Head Officers of Cities, Boroughs and Towns, not having Jurisdiction to try Felony, shall enquire of all and every offence within this Act not made Felony, and hear and determine the same.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:14"/>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:184548:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anno Primo GULIELMI &amp; MARIAE.</hi> An Act for the better Preventing the Exportation of Wooll, and Encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Woollen Manufactures of this Kingdom.</head>
            <p>WHereas through the Remisness and Negligence of Officers and others in not putting the Laws in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against the exportation of Wooll,<note place="margin">Preamble</note> Wooll-fells Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wooll-flocks, Fullers-Earth, Fulling-Clay, and Tobacco-Pipe Clay; And also by reason of the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness of some Expressions in the Statute made in the Twelfth Year of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, divers great quantities of Wooll and other the things above mentioned, have been Exported out of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> and other parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, which if not prevented for the future will tend to the utter Ruine and Undoing of many Thousands of Their Majesties Subjects, and the great diminution of the Trade of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184548:15"/> For Preventing whereof, and for the better Explanation and Execution of the Laws made against the said Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; And for preventing Frauds gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Practised to avoid the Penalties therein mentioned, Be it Enacted by the King and Queens most Excellent Majesties, by and with the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in this present Parliament As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, and by the Authority of the same,<note place="margin">Wooll car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Sea-Coasts to be En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</note> That all and every Owner of Wooll, or their Agent or Agents, that shall at any time Carry or cause to be Carried any Wooll to any Port or Place on the Sea-Coasts, with an intention to Convey the same to any other Port or Place on the Sea-Coasts within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or from the Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> from whence the same may be Shipped off, or otherwise Transported, Conveyed, or Carried into Foreign Parts, That the said Owner or Owners shall in the first place cause a due Entry to be made of the said Wooll, at the Port from whence the same shall be so intended to be Conveyed, containing the exact Weight, Marks and Numbers of the same, before he or they presume to Load or Carry away any of the said Wooll, within Five Miles of any such Port or Place on the Sea-Coasts from whence the same is so to be Conveyed.<note place="margin">Penalty</note> And if any Wooll shall be carrying to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sea without being first Entred in manner aforesaid, the Wooll so found, as also the Horse or Horses, Cart, Waggon or other Beasts, or Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages conveying the same, shall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184548:15"/> and lost: And the Person or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons Carrying, Driving, Aiding or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betting the same, shall suffer and forfeit in such manner as by the Laws and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes now in force against the Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Wooll is provided.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and it is hereby En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted and Declared, That the foregoing Clause is not intended,<note place="margin">Persons carrying Wooll from Shearing to Certifie</note> nor shall be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strued to extend to the hindring any Person or Persons, from carrying his or their Wooll from the place of Shearing the same on Horses, or by Carts and Waggons to his or their own dwelling-House or Houses, or Out-houses there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging, though the same be within Five Miles or less of the Sea, so as such person or persons, within Ten days after the shearing of the said Wooll, and before he or they remove or otherwise dispose of the same, or any part thereof, from the place where it was first carried after Shearing, do under his or their hands certifie to the Officer of the Customs in the next adjacent Port the true Quantity of the said Wooll, (that is to say) of the number of Fleeces, and where the same is housed, and that such person or persons do not remove or otherwise dispose of the said Wooll to any other place, without first certify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Officer of such Port, under his or their hands, of his intention to remove the same, Three Days at least before such removal. And the Officer and Officers in the respective Ports,<note place="margin">Register of the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates.</note> and the Limits of such Ports, are hereby required to receive and keep such Certificates, and to make a Register of them. But in case any such person or persons shall neglect to make
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184548:16"/> and send such Certificate to the Officer or Officers of the next adjacent Port, as aforesaid, or shall remove, or otherwise dispose of any of the said Wooll, before such certificate of his intention so to do, be made and delivered, as aforesaid, such person or persons shall have no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by this Proviso, but be liable to the Penalties expressed in the foregoing Clause.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Cocquet and certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate how to be made.</note> That all Cocquets for carrying Wooll from any Port within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> or from the Port of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> shall be written upon Paper and not Parchment, and Signed by Three of the chief Officers of such respective Port at least; And all Certificates of Landing the same again in any other of the said Ports, or from the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> shall be Signed in like manner; And that all such Wooll, both at Shipping and Landing, shall be Weighed in the presence of the said Officers, giving such Cocquets and Certificates respectively; And that the exact Weight, Marks, and Numbers of such Wooll, so Shipped and Landed, shall be likewise particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly expressed in both Cocquet and Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Officers Penalty.</note> That all and every such Officer or Officers as shall not observe the Directions in this Act before mentioned on their parts to be performed, shall be deemed, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged as Aiders and Abettors of the said Transportation, and suffer the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties contained in the Statutes made in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184548:16"/> the Twelfth, and Thirteenth and Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Years of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, against Transportation of Wooll, and other the things before mentioned.</p>
            <p>Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Ports of Import- and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</note> That no Wooll shall be Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but from these Ports following, <hi>(viz.) Dublin, Waterford, Youghall, Kingsale, Cork,</hi> and <hi>Drogheda;</hi> And that no Wooll shall be Imported from the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> into any Ports but these follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>(viz.) Liverpoole, Chester, Bristol, Minehead, Barnstaple, Bidiford,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the better and more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Execution of this and other Acts made against Exportation of Wooll,<note place="margin">Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners to execute the Act.</note> Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Thomas Pilkington</hi> Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Goodrick</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet, Sir <hi>Patience Ward</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Matthew Andrews,</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Benjamin Newland</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>John Matthews</hi> Kt. Sir <hi>Peter Rich</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Robert Dash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> Sir <hi>William Portman</hi> Knight and Baronet, Sir <hi>Henry Ashhurst</hi> Baronet, Sir <hi>Willam Ashhurst</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Richard Newdigate,</hi> Sir <hi>John Fleet, William Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bord, John Summers, John Sandford, Foot Onslow, John Pollexfen, Richard Brett, William Cranmore, Edward Mountague,</hi> Esquires, <hi>Samuel Hassel, William Hassel</hi> senior, <hi>John Parish, John Voyer, John Gibbon, Barnard Carter,</hi> Gentlemen, Mr. <hi>Mountague</hi> of <hi>Horten,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Samuel</hi> Baronet, <hi>William Dugdale</hi> Esq <hi>John Astley</hi> of <hi>Woley</hi> Esq Sir <hi>William Langham,</hi> Sir <hi>John Poley</hi> Knight, Sir
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184548:17"/>
               <hi>Benjamin Aylo Je</hi> Baronet, Sir <hi>Robert Jef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feries</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>John Lethuellier</hi> Kt. Sir <hi>Gabriel Roberts</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Samuel Dashwood</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Thomas Vernon</hi> Kt. <hi>Nathaniel Tench, William Hussey, Thomas Canham, William Gore, Hugh Strode, Samuel Meverell, John Smith, Thomas Firmin, Arthur Moore, William Crouch, Thomas Heatly, Thomas Sandys, William Jolly,</hi> Esquires, <hi>Paris Slaughter, Henry Cornish, John Devinck, Richard Scott, David Prole, Thomas Crandall, Philip Bickly, John Paris, Richard Harrison, John Bustfeild, John Haines, Edward Bickly, Nicholas Broking, William Stanford, Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin Ivie, Daniel Ivie, Andrew Jeffery, Thomas Turner, Peter Parr, Henry New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, Joseph Prince, Matthew Ferris, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Spry, John Keese</hi> senior, <hi>John Monk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> junior, <hi>William Wrayford, John Youat, Robert Foster, John Lavington, Thomas Potter, Robert Burridge, John p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cott, John Smith, John Mudford,</hi> or any Five of them, be Authorized for putting this and other the said Laws in execution; who are hereby impowered from time to time, by their Agents or Substitutes, to be deputed under the Hands and Seals of any Five or more of them, to seize all Wooll, Wooll-fells, and other the things above mentioned, which shall be endeavoured to be Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported contrary to this Act; and also to sue and prosecute all Persons offending against this or any the said Laws; Any Law, Custom or Usage to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:184548:17"/>
            <p>Provided always, That if any Owner of any Ship or Vessel,<note place="margin">Owner of Ships, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, their Reward.</note> or any Master or Marriner knowing of the Exportation of any Sheeps-Wooll, Wooll-fells, Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wooll flocks, Fullers Earth, Fulling-Clay, or Tobacco-Pipe Clay, contrary to the true meaning of this and the other Acts above mentioned, shall within Three Months, next after the knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or after his return into the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> or to the said Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> or into the Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> aforesaid, give the first Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>bona fina,</hi> before any of the Barons for the time being of the Court of Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer in <hi>England,</hi> or the Court of Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or before any Three of the Commissioners appointed by this Act, for the more effectual putting in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this and other Laws made against the Exportation of Wooll, or before the Head Officer of any Port where he shall first Arrive, upon his or their Oath, of the Number and Quantity of such Sheeps-wooll, Wooll-fells, Mortlings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wooll-Flocks, Fullers-earth Fulling Clay, or Tobacco Pipe Clay, so Carried, Conveyed or Exported, as aforesaid, and by whom, where, and in what Ship or Vessel, and afterwards shall be ready upon reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able warning, by Process to Justifie and Prove the same, That then such Owner and Owners, Master, Mariner and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, shall not be liable or subject to any the Penalties or Forfeitures in this or any other Act contained or Enacted, for the Offence aforesaid, but shall and is hereby enabled to recover and receive
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184548:18"/> such Benefit and Advantages as is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be allowed by the precedent Act or Acts.</p>
            <p>Provided nevertheless, That the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers given to the said Commissioners shall not hinder any Person or Persons law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Authorized from seizing Wooll,<note place="margin">Persons authorized may seize, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> or prosecuting any Person Offending against this or any former Act made against the Transportation of Wooll, and other the things above mentioned</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That if any Action, Bill, Plaint, Suit or Information shall be Commenced or Prosecuted against any Person for what he shall do in pursuance of this Act,<note place="margin">Persons Prosecuted may plead the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Issue.</note> such Persons so Sued shall and may file a Common Bail, or enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Common Appearance, and plead the general Issue, <hi>Not Guilty;</hi> And upon Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue joyned, may give this Act in Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; And if the Plaintiff or Prosecutor shall become Nonsuit, or suffer Discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, or if a Verdict pass against him, or if upon a Demurrer Judgment pass against him, the Defendant shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover treble Costs and Damages for his Molestation.</p>
            <p>And for the better Execution of the Powers granted by this Act,<note place="margin">A Register of Wooll.</note> Be it En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority aforesaid, That a Register be kept at the <hi>Custom house, London,</hi> of all the Wooll from time to time Imported from <hi>Ireland;</hi> And also of what Wooll shall be sent from one Port to another in this Kingdom; The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Weights and Numbers, the Ship, Masters name, Owners name, and to whom Consigned; To the end the said Commissioners appointed to put this Act
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184548:18"/> in Exexution, may have an Inspection thereinto, or Copies thereof from time to time This Act to continue for Three Years,<note place="margin">Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Act.</note> and from thence to the end of the next Sessions of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And for the better Encouragement of the Manufacture, as well as the Growth of Wooll, Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Woollen Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture may be export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> That from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward it shall and may be lawful to, and for any Person or Persons whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to buy any Cloth, Stuffs, Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or other Manufacture of Wooll made in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or the Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and the same freely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Molestation or Trouble whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to Export into any parts beyond the Seas, paying the usual Customs.</p>
            <p>Provided,<note place="margin">Saving to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Charters.</note> That nothing contained in this Act, shall be construed to avoid the Charters and Grants made to the <hi>Levant</hi> Company, to the <hi>Eastland</hi> Company, to the <hi>Russia</hi> Company, to the <hi>African</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, or to the Priviledges granted to them, or any of them.</p>
            <p>Provided also, and it is hereby Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That it shall and may be lawful to Transport from the Port of <hi>Southampton</hi> only,<note place="margin">Wooll from <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> only may be transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to- <hi>Guernsey,</hi> &amp;c.</note> for the only use or behoof of the Inhabitants of the Islands of <hi>Guernsey, Jersey, Alderney</hi> and <hi>Sarke,</hi> and of the Woollen Manufactures there made, One thousand Tods of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kembed Wooll for the Island of <hi>Guernsey,</hi> Two thousand Tods of unkembed Wooll for the Island of <hi>Jersey,</hi> Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Tods of unkembed Wooll for the Island of <hi>Alderney,</hi> and One hundred Tods of unkembed Wooll for the Island
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184548:19"/> of <hi>Sarke,</hi> more than by the said Act made in the Twelfth Year of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second is Directed and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the same, to be done according to the same Rules, Orders and Directions and under the like Penalties and Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as in the said Act is Directed, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, Appointed and Inflicted, and on the further Penalty of Twenty pounds for every Tod of Wooll, and Forfeiture of the Wooll it self (one half thereof to His Majesty, one quarter part thereof to the Informer, and the other quarter part to the Poor of the said Islands) in case any Person shall again Transport, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to transport any of the said Wooll, from the said Islands, for every Offence therein; And also that every Person so offending, shall from and after the First Offence be incapable of having or enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Grant of any Wooll from the said Port of <hi>Southampton,</hi> nor shall ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after have any Warrant given or granted him for that purpose; The said Penalties to be recovered by such Person as shall Sue for the same by any Action of Debt, Bill, Plaint or Information, wherein no Essoin, Protection, Priviledge, Wager of Law, Injunction or Order of Restraint is to be allowed, or any more than one Imparlance.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:184548:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anno VII &amp; VIII. GULIELMI III. Regis.</hi> An Act for the more Effectual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the Exportation of Wooll, and for the Incouraging the Importation thereof from <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas several Laws have been made to prevent the Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Wooll,<note place="margin">Preamble.</note> yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, the said Exportation is still conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, whereby daily Mischiefs and Evils do happen, and a Correspondence with <hi>France</hi> is maintained, to the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the Government, and discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the Manufacture of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And whereas in the First year of the Reign of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> there passed an Act, Intituled, <hi>An Act for the better preventing the Exportation of Wooll, and Incouraging the Woollen Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of this Kingdom,</hi> which Act was continued, by an Act made in the Fourth and Fifth years of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Intituled, <hi>An Act for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving, Continuing and Explaining several Laws therein mentioned, which are Expired
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184548:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>1 page duplicate</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:184548:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>1 page duplicate</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:184548:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>1 page duplicate</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:184548:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>1 page duplicate</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:184548:22"/> and near Expiring,</hi> and will now soon Expire.</p>
            <p>And whereas for preventing the said Mischiefs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>W.</hi> &amp; <hi>M.</hi> continued; except what is hereby al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> it is necessary the said Act should be continued, Be it therefore En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Kings most Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by the Authority of the same, That the said Act, and every Clause, Matter and Thing therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained (except what is hereafter other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise altered, explained or repealed) shall continue and remain in full force, as if the same were herein and hereby parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly recited and mentioned.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Statute of the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth and fourteenth of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second,<note place="margin">So much of the Act 13 &amp; 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. as makes Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Wooll Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed.</note> made against the Exportation of Wooll, among other things in the said Act mentioned, doth Enact the same to be deemed Felony; by the severity of which Penalty the prosecution of Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hath not been so effectually put in Execution: Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That so much of the said Act which relates to the making the said Offence Felony, be repealed and made void.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That for the better In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of the Importation of Wooll from <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ports of Import and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</note> that it shall and may be lawful for any person or persons whatsoever, from the place or places in the said Act limited, to Import into <hi>England</hi> from <hi>Ireland,</hi> any quantity or quantities of Wooll to any the Ports hereafter-mentioned (that is to say)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184548:22"/>
               <hi>Whitehaven</hi> in the County of <hi>Cumberland, Leverpoole, Chester, Bristoll, Bridgwater, Minehead, Barnstaple</hi> and <hi>Biddiford,</hi> and to no other; any thing in this Act to the contrary thereof in any wise not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms in- <hi>Ireland,</hi> shall trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of all Wooll exported thence for <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> That the Commissioners or Farmers of the Customs in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, shall from time to time, and at all times here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, once every six months, transmit or cause to be transmitted unto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners of His Majesties Customs in <hi>England,</hi> a true account of all such Wooll as shall be from time to time Exported from any of the places within the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> from whence the same may be Exported, the quantity and weight thereof, and by whom, and in what Ships exported, and where Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed, and the Names of the persons signing the Certificates of the Landing the same in <hi>England,</hi> and the Date of the said Certificates, and where the same was Landed, as also the quantity and weight contained in the said Certificates; in Order that the same may be compared with the Account by the said Act ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be kept by the Commissioners of the Customs of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And for preventing the Mischiefs of Razing, Obliterating or Interlining such Certificates, as aforesaid,<note place="margin">Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates on Paper.</note> Be it further Enacted, That all Certificates given for the Landing of Wooll from <hi>Ireland,</hi> or from one Port to another in <hi>England,</hi> shall be written upon Paper and not Parchment, and that the quantities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in expressed shall not be obliterated or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184548:23"/> Interlined upon any pretence whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>And whereas the several Inhabitants of the several Counties and Shires of this Realm,<note place="margin">Clause to prevent carrying Wooll to <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> next adjoyning to the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to the Sea-Coasts, do reap great profit and advantage by the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying out of Wooll, Wooll-fells Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Shorlings, Yarn made of Wooll, Wooll-flocks, Fullers-earth, and Souring-clay into the said Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Exporting of them into <hi>France,</hi> and other parts beyond the Seas, to the great prejudice and decay of the Woollen Manufacture of this Realm:<note place="margin">No Wooll <hi>&amp;c.</hi> shall be carried by land near the Borders of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or within five miles of the Sea, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Sun and Sun.</note> Be it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That from and after the first day of <hi>May,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hundred ninety six, no Wooll, or any other of the Commodities afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said shall be laid or loaden on any Horse, or other Carriage whatsoever, or shall be carried or conveyed by Land, to or from any place or places within the said Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties next adjoyned to the said Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or within five miles of the Sea Coast, as aforesaid, but between Sun-rising and Sun-setting, under the Penalty and Forfeiture of the said Commodities, and of the said Horses, and other Cattle and Carriages imployed in carrying the same;<note place="margin">Penalty.</note> and that no Ship or Vessel shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port or carry the same into any part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, under the Penalty and Forfeiture of the said Commodities, Ship and Vessel, and treble the value thereof, with treble Costs of Suit; and the Inhabitants of the respective Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, Port or Place exempt, next ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning to the said Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:184548:23"/> or to the Sea-Coasts out of, or through which any Wooll,<note place="margin">The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty upon the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or Port.</note> or any other of the Commodities aforesaid, shall be so carried or exported, shall forfeit Twenty pounds, if the said Wooll so car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out or exported, shall be under the value of Ten pounds, but if it shall be of greater value, then treble the value thereof so exported, or carried out of the said Kingdom, as also treble Costs of Suit; all which said Penalties, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, and Costs of Suit, are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and received by him or them that shall Sue for the same, and to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted by any Action of Debt, Suit, Bill, Plaint or Information, against the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of such Hundred, Port or Place exempt, out of, or through which the said Wooll, or other Commodities shall be exported, in any of his Majesties Courts of Record at <hi>Westminster,</hi> where no Essoin, Protection, or Wager of Law shall be allowed, nor any more than one Imparlance.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Execution for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, shall be had on the Hundred, as in case of Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by <hi>Stat.</hi> 27. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 13.</note> That the Execution for the Informer, shall and may be had against two or more of the said Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; and that after Execution had by force of this Act, it shall and may be lawful (upon complaint made by the Party or Parties so charged) to and for the Justices of the Peace of the same County or Place, where any such Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution shall be had, at their General Quarter-Sessions to be held for the said County or Place, to Assess and Tax rata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and proportionably, according to their Discretions, all and every the Towns, Parishes, Villages and Hamlets
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184548:24"/> in the said Hundred, Port or Place ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt, in the same manner and form as any Hundred ought to be charged in case of Robbery committed, for the persons against whom Execution shall be had for the person so Robbed, pursuant to an Act made in the Seven and twentieth Year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Intituled, <hi>An Act for the Following of the Hue and Cry;</hi> And that the Justices of the Peace of the said County or Place where such Fact shall be committed, shall and are hereby impowred and required at their General Quarter-Sessions, to be held for the said County or Place, to levy the Penalties hereby charged upon the said Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants by an equal Assessment upon the said Inhabitants, and reimburse such person or persons, Inhabitants within the said Hundred, Port or Place exempt, adjacent to the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or the Sea-Coasts, from whence the said Wooll, or other the said Commodities shall be transported, in the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if there had been a Judgment at Law against the said Hundred, Port or Place exempt.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Aiders or Abetters shall suffer three years Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> That all persons who shall be aiding, abetting or assisting in carrying or exporting any of the said Commodities out of this Realm, as aforesaid, (being legally convicted thereof) shall suffer Three years Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment,<note place="margin">Owners shall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</note> without Bail or Mainprize, and the Owner of the said Wooll, or of any other of the Commodities afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, and all and every person or persons who shall be aiding, abetting or assisting in carrying or exporting of them or any
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:184548:24"/> of them out of this Kingdom, shall answer and satisfie treble the value of all such Forfeitures and penalties which such In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants shall be so charged with,<note place="margin">Treble costs of Suit.</note> and liable to, as also treble Costs of Suit; which shall and may be recovered by Action of Debt, Suit, Bill Plaint or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in any of his Majesties Courts of Record at <hi>Westminster,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How reco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verable.</note> wherein no Essoin, Protection or Wager of Law shall be allowed nor any more than one Imparlance, by, and in the Name of the Clerk of the Peace for the time being, of, or for every such County or Place, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naming the Christian Name, or Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name of the said Clerk of the Peace; which treble Value and treble Costs of Suit, shall be to the only use and behoof of the said Inhabitants; and that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the Death or removal of any such Clerk of the Peace after such Action of Debt, Suit, Bill, Plaint or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, sued, commenced or prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the same shall be prosecuted and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued to Judgment and Execution, in such manner and form, to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, as that Clerk of the Peace might have done which first commenced or preferred the said Action of Debt, Suit, Bill, Plaint or Information.</p>
            <p>And for the better and more impartial Tryals of all such Actions and Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which shall be commenced or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted by virtue of this Act,<note place="margin">Jury shall be of any other County than that wherein the Fact was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</note> Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That such Actions and Informations shall be tryed in any of his Majesties Courts of Record, by a Jury of good and lawful freehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to be summoned out of any other Country than that wherein the Fact shall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:184548:25"/> be committed, and to encourage persons to discover the said Crime,<note place="margin">The three first Aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</note> the first three persons who have been aiding, abetting or assisting in carrying out or exporting of Wooll, or any other of the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as aforesaid, that shall inform thereof any justice of the Peace in either of the said several Counties aforesaid, whereby the Punishment and Penalties appointed by this Act, may be inflicted and recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Party or Parties so discovering (not being Owner or Part Owners of the said Wooll or other Commodities afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said) shall not suffer any of the said Penalties or Punishment.<note place="margin">except the Owners.</note>
               <note place="margin">Action a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> shall be in the proper County.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if any Action or Suit shall be brought and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted by any person or persons against any Justice of Peace, or other person imployed by them or any of them, in the execution of this Act, for any Matter, Cause or Thing by them, or either of them done, committed or executed by virtue or reason of this Act, or any Clause or Article therein contained, That then and in every such Case, the Action shall be levyed in the proper County where the Fact was done and committed, and not elsewhere; and the Defendant or Defendants may plead the General Issue, and give the special Matter in Evidence at the Tryal, That the same was done in pursuance, and by Authority of this Act; And if upon examination it shall so hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be done, the Jury shall find for the Defendant or Defendants; and in such case, or if the Plaintiff shall be Nonsuit, or discontinue his Action after the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant or Defendants hath or have appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:184548:25"/> the Defendant or Defendants shall have and recover their treble Costs, which he or they shall sustain, or be put unto by reason of his or their wrongful Vexation in defence of the said Action or Suit; and that every Action, Suit, Bill,<note place="margin">Suit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a year after Fact commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> Plaint or Information, by virtue of this Act, shall be commenced and prosecuted within one year after the Fact committed.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That if any person who is Intituled to the Penalties and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures by this Act given,<note place="margin">Penalty upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding.</note> shall compound with any Hundred, Port or Place exempt, hereby liable to pay the same, for any lesser Sum than what is hereby given, That it shall at any time hereafter, be lawful for any other person to Sue for and Recover the same in manner and form, as aforesaid, as if no such Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition had been made, and the person so compounding, shall for such his Offence suffer five years Imprisonment without Bail or Mainprize; and this Act to continue in force for three years,<note place="margin">Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Act.</note> and from thence to the end of the next Session of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And for the better preventing the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Wooll,<note place="margin">Admiralty shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Cruizers.</note> and Correspondence with <hi>France,</hi> Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That the Lord High Admiral of <hi>England</hi> or Commissioners for executing the Office of Lord High Admiral for the time being, shall from time to time direct and appoint, one Ship of the Fifth Rate, and two Ships of the Sixth Rate, and four Armed Sloops, constantly to cruize from off the <hi>North-foreland</hi> to the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> with orders for taking and seizing all Ships, Vessels or Boats, which shall export any Wooll, or carry or bring any prohibited Goods, or any su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected Persons.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:184548:26"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anno IX &amp; X. GULIELMI III. Regis.</hi> An Act for the Explanation and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Execution of former Acts made against Transportation of Wooll, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Earth and Scouring Clay.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preamble.</note>WHereas several Laws have been made to prevent the exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Wooll and Fullers earth out of this Kingdom, yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless the said Exportation is still no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriously continued, to the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and discouragement of the Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Trade and Manufacture of <hi>England:</hi> And whereas in the First Year of the Reign of his present Majesty King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and the late Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> there passed an Act,<note place="margin">1 <hi>W.</hi> &amp; <hi>M.</hi>
               </note> Intituled, <hi>An Act for the better Preventing the Exportation of Wooll, and Encouraging the Woollen Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of this Kingdom;</hi> which Act was continued by one other Act made in the Fourth and Fifth Years of Their said Majesties Reign,<note place="margin">4 &amp; 5 <hi>W.</hi> &amp; <hi>M.</hi>
               </note> Intituled, <hi>An Act for Reviving, Continuing and Explaining se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Laws therein mentioned, which were Expired and near Expiring;</hi> Which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184548:26"/> said Act was further continued in the Seventh year of His present Majesties Reign, with some Alterations, Intituled, <hi>An Act for the more effectual preventing the Exportation of Wooll from</hi> Ireland;<note place="margin">7 <hi>W.</hi> 3.</note> which Act is now near expiring: And whereas for preventing the said mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs it is necessary the said last men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Act, with some convenient alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, should be continued, and also that there should be some more effectual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies than hath been hitherto provided, Be it therefore Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by and with the consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by the Authority of the same, That the said last mentioned Act, made in the Seventh year of his Majesties Reign, and Intituled, <hi>An Act for the more effectual preventing the exportation of Wooll,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 <hi>W.</hi> 3. continued.</note>
               <hi>and for encouraging the importation of Wooll from</hi> Ireland, and every clause, matter and thing therein contained, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept what is hereby otherwise altered, explained, enlarged or repealed, shall continue and be in full Force, as if the same were herein and hereby particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly recited and mentioned.</p>
            <p>And whereas under a pretention of carrying Fullers Earth and Scouring Clay into <hi>Ireland,</hi> the same is conveyed into <hi>Scotland</hi> and other Foreign Parts, to the further prejudice of the Woolled Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture of this Kingdom,<note place="margin">After 24. <hi>June,</hi> 1698. No Fullers earth or Scouring Clay shall be export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> Be it further Enacted, That from and after the Four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand six hundred ninety eight, no Fullers Earth or Scouring Clay shall be exported out of this Kingdom, Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:184548:27"/> or Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> into <hi>Ireland, Scotland,</hi> or into any other Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Parts, upon any pretence whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever but that the Exporters, being le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally Convicted, shall be liable to the Forfeitures of One Shilling for every Pound Weight.<note place="margin">Penalty.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas it is a common practice in <hi>Romney Marsh</hi>
               <note place="margin">Romney Marsh.</note> and other Places adjacent, for evil disposed persons to sheer their Sheep, and Lodge Wooll near the Sea-side, and sometimes to bring Wooll out of the Countrey more remote, and Lodge it, as aforesaid, where by fraud and force, in the night time, the said persons do cause the same to be transported to <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trade of <hi>France</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased by our Wooll. Wooll lodged within 10 Miles of the Sea, in <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex,</hi> Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er shall give an account within three days after shearing and the like notice upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval,</note> to the increase of the Trade of that kingdom, and the destruction of the Trade of <hi>England:</hi> To prevent these pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices for the future, be it further Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Authority aforesaid, That all and every Owner and Owners of Wooll shorn or housed, laid up or lodged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Ten Miles of the Sea-side, within the Counties of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Sussex,</hi> shall be obliged to give an exact account in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, within three days after the shearing thereof, of his, her or their Number of Fleeces, and where lodged or housed, to the next adjoyning Port, or Officer of His Majesties Customs; and the like notice before he, she or they shall presume to remove any part or parcel thereof, of the said number of Fleeces and Weight; and the name and abode of the person or persons to whom it is disposed; and the place to which it is intended to be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;<note place="margin">and take a Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</note> and to take a Certificate from the Officer who first entred the same, upon the Penalty of Forfeiting all such Wooll
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:184548:27"/> as shall not be so entred or otherwise disposed of, and the Owner or Owners also to be liable to the further Penalties of Three Shillings for every Pound weight of all such Wooll,<note place="margin">Penalty.</note> as if the same had been actually transported; which said Account the Officers respectively are hereby required to take <hi>gratis,</hi> and to give such Certificate or Certificates, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, to the party or parties de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the same, and shall therein spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the Name or Names of the Owners and Buyers thereof, and limit it to such times and places to be removed; for which Duty and Service the said Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer or Officers shall take and demand the Sum of Six Pence and no more for each Certificate,<note place="margin">6 <hi>d.</hi> for every Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</note> upon any account or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatsoever.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is a common Practice in the said Marsh, for divers persons not Resident upon the place, to buy up great quantities of Wooll, and transport, or cause the same to be transported out of this Kingdom:<note place="margin">Persons buying Wooll within 15 Miles of the Sea in <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Sussex,</hi> shall give Bond to the King.</note> For preventing such Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices for the future, Be it further Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Authority aforesaid, That no person or persons Residing within Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Miles of the Sea, in the said Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Sussex,</hi> shall presume to Buy any Wooll, before they do enter in to Bond to the Kings Majesty, His Heirs or Successors, with Sureties, that all the Wooll they buy shall not be sold by them to any person or persons within Fifteen Miles of the Sea;<note place="margin">Wooll carried to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Sea, not entred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited.</note> and in case any Wooll be found carrying towards the Sea-side in the Counties aforesaid, unless such Wooll be first entred, and security given, the same shall be Forfeited, and the person
<pb facs="tcp:184548:28"/> or persons offending therein,<note place="margin">and Three shillings <hi>per</hi> Pound Weight.</note> shall also Forfeit Three Shillings for every Pound weight of all such Wooll.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Wooll.</note> That no Wooll removed from the place where it was first housed, lodged or laid after Shearing, within Ten Miles, as aforesaid, shall be lodged after the first removing within Fifteen Miles of the Sea, in the Counties aforesaid, upon pain of forfeiting all such Wooll, if found; but if carried away, then every person or persons who were the Owners of the said Wooll, to forfeit for every Pound weight the Sum of Three Shillings.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Distance of Miles on Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> That all and every person or persons that shall lay, or cause to be laid or hid any Wooll, within Fifteen Miles of the Sea, and not entred, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid,<note place="margin">Persons laying Claim to Wooll seized shall give Security.</note> all such Wooll shall be seized and forfeited, That upon any seizure of such Wooll, every person laying claim to the same, shall give sufficient Security in His Majesties Court of Exchequer (if cast upon Tryal) to Pay Treble Costs, over and above the Penalties and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Persons Sued may Plead the general Issue.</note> That if any Action or Suit shall be brought and Prosecuted by any person or persons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any person imployed in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Act, for any matter, clause or thing by them or either of them done, committed or executed by virtue of this Act, or any clause or article therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that then and in every such case, the Defendant or Defendants may Plead the General Issue, and give the special
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184548:28"/> Matter in Evidence at the Tryal, that the same was done in pursuance and by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Act; And if upon Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it shall so happen to be done, the Jury shall find for the Defendant or Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants: And in such case, or if the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff shall be Nonsuit, or discontinue his Action, the Defendant or Defendants shall have and recover treble Costs, which he or they shall sustain or be put unto, by reason of his or their wrongful Vexation in Defence of the said Action or Suit.</p>
            <p>And it is hereby further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures be
<list>
                     <item>1 Third to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, and</item>
                     <item>2 Thirds to the Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> That all the Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Penalties before in this Act men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, shall be distributed in manner and form following, <hi>viz.</hi> One third part to the Use of His Majesty, His Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, and the other Two thirds to the use of such person or persons as shall Seize or Sue for the same, by Bill, Plaint or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in any of His Majesties Courts at <hi>Westminster,</hi> wherein no Essoin, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection or Wager of Law shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And whereas by an Act of Parliament made in the Twelfth year of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second,<note place="margin">12 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc></desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It is Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That no person or persons whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever should, at any time thereafter, be Impeached for any Offence against the said Act, unless such persons be Prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within One year next ensuing such Offence committed: And whereas a great many persons who have been guilty of transporting Wooll, but discovery thereof hath not been made till the expiration of Twelve months after the Offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, to the great encouragement of several notorious Offenders; For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention whereof, Be it Enacted by the
<pb facs="tcp:184548:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>1 page duplicate</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:184548:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>1 page duplicate</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:184548:30"/> Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Wooll may be Sued at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time within 3 years after Offence Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> That it shall and may be lawful for His Majesty, to cause such person or persons as are or shall be guilty of transporting or causing to be transported any Wooll, Wooll-fells, Fullers Earth or Scouring Clay, to be Sued and Prosecuted at any time within Three years after the Offence committed, in the same manner as Informations, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Penal Statutes, have been usually, and may lawfully be Prosecuted.</p>
            <p>And for the better preventing the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Wooll into <hi>S otland</hi> from <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clause to prevent Wooll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> Be it further Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, That from and after the said Four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> all and every Owner or Owners of Wooll Shorn, Laid up or Lodged within Fifteen Miles of the Borders of <hi>Scotland</hi> shall and are hereby required to give an exact Account of his,<note place="margin">Registring pursuant to 1 <hi>W.</hi> &amp; <hi>M. cap.</hi> 32.</note> her or their Number of Fleeces, and where Lodged or Housed, to such person or persons as shall be Appointed and Impowered for that purpose, pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to the direction or true meaning of the aforesaid Act of Parliament, made in the First year of His present Majesty and the late Queen; Which person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons shall give attendance for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, at the several Ports and Market Towns, within the aforesaid distance of Fifteen Miles; And shall and are hereby required to make a true Entry of such Wooll, in a Book to be kept for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose;<note place="margin">Penalty upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving without Licence.</note> and in case any Owner or Owners of such Wooll, shall neglect or refuse to give such Account to such person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, as shall after such notice given re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move such Wooll, or any part of it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Licence from such person or persons
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:184548:30"/> as shall have made such entry, he, she or they so neglecting or refusing, or remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving afterwards his, her or their Wooll, or any part of it, without Licence, as aforesaid, shall forfeit Three Shillings for every Pound Weight of such Wooll; And all the Wooll that shall be found within the distance aforesaid, of the Borders of <hi>Scotland</hi> not Entred, as aforesaid, shall be, and is hereby forfeited, One third Part to His Majesty, His Heirs and Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, and the other Two third Parts to him or them who shall Sue for the same, in any of His Majesties Courts of Record at <hi>Westminster,</hi> in which no Essoin, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection or Wager of Law, or more than One Imparlance shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And whereas by an Act made in the Parliament held in the Seventh and Eighth Years of His present Majesty, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,<note place="margin">7 &amp; 8 <hi>W.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 28</note>
               <hi>An Act for the more effectual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the exportation of Wooll, and for the incouraging the importation thereof from</hi> Ireland, amongst other things it is Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the Hundred out of which any Wooll shall be exported, be liable to such Penalties and Forfeitures as is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the said Act: But the Hundred of <hi>Winchelsea</hi> in the Cinque Ports, being divided by a Navigable Arm of the Sea, so that the Inhabitants on the one side thereof cannot be privy to, or prevent what is done by those of the other: Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Winchel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sea</hi>-Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</note> That the said Hundred of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelsea</hi> shall be deemed and taken, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to the said Act, as Two distinct Hundreds (that is to say) the Part of the one side of the said arm of the Sea as one Hundred, and the Part on the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:184548:31"/> other side as one other intire Hundred; and the Penalties which may be Forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for suffering such Exportation, shall Affect, Charge and be Levied on that Part only of the said Hundred which lies on the same side of the said Arm of the Sea, out of which such Exportation was made and permitted, any thing in this or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Act to the contrary notwithstanding. Provided nevertheless, That nothing in this Act shall be construed to extend to divide the said Hundred in any other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular but in this only.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:184548:31"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anno XIV. CAROLI II. Regis.</hi> An Act to restrain the Exportation of Leather and raw Hides out of the Realm of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas notwithstanding the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good Laws before this time made, and still in force, prohibiting the exportation of Leather out of this Realm; and the Penalty by those Acts imposed, by the cunning and subtilty of some persons, and the neglect of others who ought to take care thereof, there are such quantities of Leather dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exported to Foreign Parts, that the price of Leather is grown to those Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive Rates, that many Artificers work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Leather, cannot Furnish themselves with sufficient store thereof, for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of their Trades; and the poor sort of people are not able to buy those things made of Leather, which of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity they must make use of:</p>
            <p>For redress of which Griefs, Be it enacted by the Kings most excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:184548:32"/> assembled,<note place="margin">What Skins or Hides tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, may not be Transport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> That from and after the first day of <hi>May</hi> now next ensuing, no person or persons whatsoever, shall carry or transport, or cause to be carried or transported out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Scotland, Ireland,</hi> or into any the Isles belonging to this Kingdom, or to any parts beyond the Seas, the Skins or Hides tanned or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanned of any Ox, Steer, Bull, Cow or Calf, otherwise, or in any other manner than is by this present Act directed</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That none of the Skins or Hides aforesaid, which sha l happen to be taken from any of the Beasts afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, within any Island whatsoever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> (except <hi>Ireland</hi>) shall be transported out of that Island, into any other place but into the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> upon pain of forfeiture for every such offence, double the value of the Skins or Hides so to be transported out of the said Island or any of them, to any other place than into the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> the same for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture to be sued for and disposed as hereafter in this Act is directed.</p>
            <p>And for the better preventing of such mischiefs as are intended to be remedied by this Act,<note place="margin">What Leather must be bought on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in open Fairs or Markets for selling Leather.</note> Be it enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid, That all red tanned Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made of the Hides or Skins of any the beasts aforesaid, of what kind or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture soever, shall be bought only in the open and Common Fair or Market used for the putting of Leather to sale, and not in any House, Tanners Yard, Shop, or other place whatsoever, on pain that such person or persons that shall not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly do the same, shall for every
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:184548:32"/> such offence forfeit the same Leather,<note place="margin">The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> or the value thereof, and the contract for the sale thereof shall be void; and all such Leather shall be searched and sealed by the Searchers and Sealers thereunto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, before the same be put to sale, and upon such sale shall be registred, and a true Entry thereof made both by the Buyer and Seller, who are both to be present at such Registring thereof, and both their names and places of abode entred into the Book of the said Register, on pain that every such Buyer or Seller that shall not accordingly do the same, shall for every such Offence forfeit the same Leather, or the value thereof, and the forfeiture shall be recovered and employed in such manner as hereafter in this Act is directed.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Penalty for Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of any Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or raw Hides.</note> That if any person or persons shall be found guilty of the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of any Leather, or raw Hides of any the Beasts aforesaid (excepting such Calves Skins and Sheep Skins, dressed without the Wooll, as by Law may be transported) contrary to the provision of this Act, he shall from thenceforth be disabled to trade or deal in Leather for the future, and shall for every such Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence forfeit the Sum of Five hundred pounds, to be sued for, and disposed as hereafter in this Act is directed.</p>
            <p>Provided nevertheless, That this Act, or any thing therein contained, shall not extend to the prohibiting the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of any Leather made into Boots, Shoes or Slippers, but that the same may be transported; any thing in this Act contained to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:184548:33"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Who may search and seize Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Hides intended to be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</note>And be it further enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That it shall and may be lawful to and for the respective Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and Wardens of the Cordwainers, Sadlers, Girdlers and Curriers of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and their Deputies, and all Customers, Comptrollers, Farmers of Customs, Supervisors, Searchers, and other Officers belonging to the Customs, and to and for all Justices of the Peace, Mayors, and chief Officers of Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions within this Realm, Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> from time to time, as well by Land as by Water, to search for, and seize any Leather, or raw Hides wrought or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought, cut or uncut, packed up or unpacked, intended or purposed to be transported by any person or persons into any parts beyond the Seas, or into <hi>Scotland,</hi> other than Calves Skins and Sheep Skins, as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And whereas divers Tanners do shave, cut and rake their upper-leather Hides all over,<note place="margin">Shaving of Leather by Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> and the Necks of their backs and buts, to the great impairing thereof, and the extream prejudice of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Be it therefore enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That every Tanner, who after the Nine and twentieth day of <hi>September,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hundred sixty and two, shall commit any such Offence, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, shall forfeit all the said Leather, Backs,<note place="margin">The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> Buts or Calves Skins so shaved, cut or raked, or the value thereof, and it shall be lawful for the Searchers and Sealers of Leather to seize the same.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Leaden-Hall, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note>And be it further Enacted, That the Market for Leather in <hi>Leaden-Hall</hi> in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:184548:33"/>
               <hi>London,</hi> shall be kept on the <hi>Tuesday,</hi> as now it is; any Law, Usage or Custom to the contrary in any wise notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">How the Penalties shall be recovered.</note> That all the penalties and forfeitures, and every sum or sums of money for any offence or offences herein before mentioned, shall be recovered by Action of Debt, Bill, Plaint, or Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be brought for the same in any Court or Courts at <hi>Westminster,</hi> or in any Court or Courts of Record in the City, Town, County or Place where the said offence shall be committed, wherein no Wager of Law, Protection or Essoin shall be admitted, neither shall the same be removed out of the said County, City or Town-corporate; the one half of the said Forfeitures to be to the use of the Kings Majesty, His Heirs and Successors, and the other half thereof to the use of the Informer or Informers that shall sue for the fame.</p>
            <p>Provided also, and be it Enacted,<note place="margin">Transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Leather declared a common Nusance.</note> That all such Exportation, or Transportation of any Hides or Leather, contrary to this Act, is hereby adjudged and declared to be a common and publick Nusance.</p>
            <p>Provided nevertheless, That this Act shall not extend,<note place="margin">Leather for neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary use of Ships in Voyages.</note> or be construed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit the carrying or conveying of any such Hides or Leather, which shall be used or employed for the necessary use, or provision of any Ship or Vessel in any Voyage beyond the Seas, and which shall not be sold in any Foreign Parts, so as the number do not exceed six raw Hides, and three Tanned Hides.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:184548:34"/>
            <p>Provided always nevertheless, and be it further enacted by the authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said,<note place="margin">Artificers dealing in cutting of Leather in <hi>London,</hi> or within three miles thereof.</note> That all and every Artificer dealing in cutting of Leather, or other person or persons whatsoever, which shall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter buy any red tanned Leather within the City of <hi>London,</hi> or three miles thereof, shall before the next Market day within the said place for sale of Leather, give notice thereof to one or more of the Company of Curriers then exercising and using the Art and Mystery of a Currier within the said City of <hi>London,</hi> and three miles thereof, and within three weeks after such notice shall deliver, or cause to be delivered the said Leather so bought, except such part thereof as shall be used for Soles, without being Curried, Tallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or Dressed, unto the said Currier or Curriers to whom such notice was given, to the intent that the same may be Curried, Tallowed, or otherwise Dressed, as is directed and appointed by one Act made in the first year of King <hi>James,</hi> Chapter twenty second, touching the Duty of Tanners, Curriers, Shoe-Makers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, upon penalty of the forfeiture of Six shillings eight pence for every Back, Butt, Hide or Calves Skin so bought, and not delivered,<note place="margin">Leather used in <hi>London,</hi> or within three miles, to be search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers there.</note> as aforesaid, for the uses, and to be recovered, as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is Enacted amongst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, by the said Act made in the first year of King <hi>James,</hi> That no person or persons shall by any means occupy, or put in any Made-wares within the City of <hi>London,</hi> or three miles of the same City, any Curried Leather before the same shall be searched and allowed by the Wardens of the Curriers of <hi>London</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:184548:34"/> for the time being, or such person as they shall thereto assign, and be sealed with a Seal therefore to be prepared, upon pain that every Shoe-maker and other Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, Cutter of Leather, offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that Article, should forfeit for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Hide or Skin otherwise Curried or employed, as is aforesaid,<note place="margin">The pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> Six shillings eight pence, and the value of every such Hide or Skin: Be it therefore further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the authority aforesaid, That the Master and Wardens of the Company of Curriers for the time being, or such persons as they shall thereto assign, shall from time to time, and at all seasonable times in the day-time, enter into any Ware-house, Shop, Cellar, or other place within the said City of <hi>London,</hi> or three miles of the same City, belonging unto any of the said Cordwainers, Sadlers, Girdlers, or other person or persons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Artificers, dealing in cutting Leather, and in the presence of any two or more of them, to search for, and seize all such Leather intended to be prohibited to be used by the said Clause, Branch or Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, as aforesaid, as also for all Wares made of such Leather;<note place="margin">Penalties for oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the Searching.</note> And if any such person or persons, Artificers or Dealers, as aforesaid, shall oppose or refuse to permit the said Master and Wardens of the Company of Curriers, or such persons as they shall thereto assign, to make any such search or seizure, as aforesaid, he or they shall forfeit for every such Offence the sum of Twenty Pounds for the Uses, and to be recovered, as aforesaid; And if any of the said Artificers and Dealers in cutting of Leather, do refuse to be present with the said Searchers, whenso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:184548:35"/> the same shall be desired by the said Master and Wardens of the Company of Curriers, or such persons thereto assign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, as aforesaid, then for every such default the persons so refusing shall forfeit the sum of Ten pounds for the Uses, and to be recovered, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:184548:35"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anno X &amp; XI. GULIELMI III. Regis.</hi> An Act to prevent the Exportation of Wooll out of the Kingdoms of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> into Foreign parts; And for the Encouragement of the Woollen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures in the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOrasmuch as Wooll and the Woollen Manufactures of Cloth, Serge, Bays,<note place="margin">Preamble.</note> Kerseys and other Stuffs made or mixed with Wooll, are the greatest and most profitable Commodities of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, on which the value of Lands, and the Trade of the Nation do chiefly depend: And whereas great Quantities of the like Manufactures have of late been made, and are daily increasing in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in the <hi>English</hi> Plantations in <hi>America,</hi> and are exported from thence to Foreign Markets, heretofore supplied from <hi>England,</hi> which will inevitably sink the Value of Lands, and tend to the ruine of the Trade, and the Woollen Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of this Realm: For the Preventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, and for the Encouragement of the Woollen Manufactures within this Kingdom, Be it Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by and with the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:184548:36"/> Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by the Authority of the same,<note place="margin">No person after 24 <hi>June,</hi> 1699. shall Export Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from <hi>Ireland,</hi> for Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign parts.</note> That no person or persons whatsoever, from and after the Four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ninety nine, shall directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly Export, Transport, Ship off, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Convey, or Cause or Procure to be Exported, Transported, Shipped off, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or Conveyed out of, or from the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> into any Foreign Realm, States or Dominions, or into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts or places whatsoever, other than the parts within the Kingdom of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> or the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> any the Wooll, Wooll-fells, Shortlings, Mortlings, Wooll-flocks, Worsted, Bay, or Woollen Yarn, Cloth, Serge, Bays, Kerseys, Says, Prizes, Druggets, Cloth-Serges, Shalloons, or any other Drapery Stuffs or Woollen Manufactures whatsoever, made up or mixed with Wooll or Wooll-flocks;<note place="margin">Nor carry, load or board any Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> or shall directly or indirectly Load or cause to be Loaden upon any Horse, Cart or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Carriage, or Load or Lay on Board, or cause to be Laden or Laid on Board in any Ship or Vessel, in any place or parts within, or belonging to the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> any such Wooll, Wooll-fells, Shortlings, Mortlings, Wooll-flocks, Worsted, Bay, or Woollen Yarn, Cloth, Bays, Kerseys, Serges, Says, Frizes, Druggets, Cloth-Serges, Shalloons, or any other Drapery or Woollen Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, to the Intent or Purpose to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, Transport, Ship off, Carry or Convey the same, or cause the same to be Exported, Transported, Shipped off,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:184548:36"/> Carried or Conveyed out of the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or out of any Port or Place belonging to the same, or with Intent or Purpose, that any person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons whatsoever, should so Export, Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, Ship off, Carry or Convey the same out of the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> into any Ports or Places (except as aforesaid.)</p>
            <p>And be it Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid,<note place="margin">Penalty, Forfeiture of the Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> That all and every of the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Offenders, Offence and Offences aforesaid, shall be subject and liable to the respective pains and penalties, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures hereafter following (that is to say) The said Wooll, Wooll-fells, Shortlings, Mortlings, Wooll-flocks, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, Bay, or Woollen Yarn, Cloth, Serge, Bays, Kerseys, Says, Prizes, Druggets, Cloth-Serges, Shalloons, or any other Draperies, Stuffs or any other Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, made of or mixed with Wooll or Wooll-flocks, so Exported, Transported, Shipped off or Carried, Conveyed or Loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, contrary to the true intent and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Act, shall be forfeited;<note place="margin">and 50<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc></desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </note> and that every of the Offender and Offenders therein, shall likewise forfeit the sum of Five hundred pounds for every such Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; And all and every Ship, Vessel,<note place="margin">Ship, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Forfeited with all her Tackle</note> Barge, Boat, or other Bottom whatsoever, wherein any of the said Commodities are or shall be Shipped or Laid on Board, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true intent and meaning of this Act, shall be forfeited, with all her Tackle, Apparel and Furniture to them and every of them belonging;<note place="margin">Masters, Mariners, Porters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> assisting, Forfeit 40 <hi>l.</hi>
               </note> And the Masters and Mariners thereof, or any Porters, Carriers, Waggoners, Boat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or other persons whatsoever, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such Offence, and wittingly aiding and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:184548:37"/> assisting therein, shall forfeit fourty Pounds;<note place="margin">Forfeiture how to be disposed of.</note> of which one moiety shall be to him or them that shall Sue for the same by Bill, Plaint or Information in any of His Majesties Courts of Record in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the other moiety thereof to the Encouragement of setting up the Linen Manufactures in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be disposed of by the Court of Exchequer there for that use only; In which Suit no Essoin, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection or Wager of Law, or more than one Imparlance shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And to prevent evading the Penalties of this Act,<note place="margin">Acquittals in <hi>Ireland,</hi> no Bar to Prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions here.</note> by pretention of prosecution or Acquittals in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That no Acquittal nor any Indictment, Information or Suit (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less the Offender be thereupon Convicted) in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for any Offence provided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst in this Act, shall be pleaded or allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Bar or Delay of any Indictment, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, Suit or Prosecution within the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Lawful to Seize and Convey to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties next Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house such Wooll, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </note> That it shall and may be Lawful to and for any person or persons to seize, take, secure and convey to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties next Ware-house all such Wooll, Wooll-fells, Shortlings, Mortlings, Wooll-flocks, Worsted, Bay, or Woollen Yarn, Cloth, Serges, Bays, Kerseys, Says, Frizes, Druggets, Cloth-Serges, Shalloons, Stuffs, and other Draperies and Woollen Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, or mixed with Wooll or Wooll-flocks, as he or they shall happen to see, find, know or discover to be laid on Board in any Ship, Vessel or Boat, or to be brought, carried or laid on Shore, at or near the Sea, or any Navigable River or Water, to the intent or purpose to be Exported or
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:184548:37"/> Conveyed out of the said Kingdom of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> contrary to the true meaning of this Act, or to be Laden upon any Horse, Cart or other Carriage, to the intent or purpose to be Exported, Conveyed or Carried into any Foreign parts or places, contrary to the true intent and meaning hereof;<note place="margin">And also the Ship, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> And also that it shall and may be lawful to and for any person and persons to seize, and secure all and every such Ship, Hulk, Vessel, Barge or Boat, of what kind soever, or wheresoever found or discovered, wherein any of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Commodities shall happen to be Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped or put on Board, contrary to the true intent and meaning of this Act; And that such person or persons that shall happen so to seize, take or secure any of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities aforesaid, or any such Ship, Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel, Hulk, Barge or Boat, as aforesaid, shall be Indemnified for so doing, to all intents and purposes.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Bond to be given for Wooll from <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> That for every Ship or Vessel, which from and after the said Four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> shall set out and sail from the said Kingdom of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in order to export or carry off any of the Commodities aforesaid to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Bond shall be given by two sufficient persons, known Inhabitants of, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siding in or near the place where the Bond is or shall be given, to the Chief Officers of the Customs, belonging to the said Port or Place in the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> from whence the said Ship or Vessel shall set Sail, in double the value of any the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid Goods, intended to be Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, as aforesaid, before the said Ship or Vessel shall be permitted to Lade on Board
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:184548:38"/> any of the Commodities aforesaid, with condition that if the said Ship or Vessel shall Lade or Take on Board, any of the said Goods, in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that then and in such case all the said Goods shall be brought by the same Ship or Vessel, to some Port or Ports within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Wales,</hi> as aforesaid, and shall there Unlade or Put on Shore the same, and pay the Custom and Duties thereof, (the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Seas only excepted;) And that every Ship or Vessel, which shall Lade or Take on Board any of the said Goods, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til such Bond be given, shall be Forfeited, to be Recovered and Imployed in manner as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Register to be kept at the Custom-house, <hi>London.</hi>
               </note>And for the more effectual Execution of the powers granted by this Act, Be it enacted by the authority aforesaid. That a Register be kept at the Custom-House in <hi>London,</hi> of all the aforesaid Goods, from time to time, Imported from <hi>Ireland,</hi> into any of the Ports within this Kingdom, or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Wales,</hi> with the particular Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Quantities thereof, the Master and Owners Names, and to whom Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Cockets, Warrants and Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates, how to be written and signed.</note> That all Cockets and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants for the Carrying or Transporting of any of the aforesaid Goods, from the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to any Port or Ports aforesaid, within this Kingdom, shall be written upon Paper and not Parchment, and Signed by Three of the Chief Officers of such respective Port at least, and all Certificates of Landing the same in any the Ports aforesaid, within this Kingdom, or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> shall be Signed in like
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:184548:38"/> manner;<note place="margin">Goods to be search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both at Shipping and Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed upon the Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates.</note> And that all the goods afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, both at Shipping and Landing, shall be Viewed and Examined by the Surveyor or Searcher, or Land-waiter, Attending the Shipping or Discharge of any the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Goods; And that the exact Quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Qualities, Marks and Numbers of the Goods aforesaid, so Shipped in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> shall be particularly Expressed and Indorsed upon the Cocket, by which the said Goods are or were to be Shipped, and likewise upon the Warrant for Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the same in <hi>England,</hi> and also upon the Certificate or Certificates, Given or to be Given, for Discharging the Bond or Bonds taken in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the same.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid,<note place="margin">The quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and quantities of such Goods, and Dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates of the Bonds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be transmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> That the Commissioners of the Revenue, or Farmers of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms, or of the Revenue of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, shall from time to time, and at all times hereafter once within every six months, or within Thirty days after the end thereof, Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or cause to be Transmitted unto the Commissioners or Farmers of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Customs in <hi>England,</hi> of all such Goods as aforesaid, as shall from time to time be Exported from the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Qualities and Quantities thereof, and Duplicates of the Bonds ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for Lading the same, and by whom and in what Ships Exported, and where and to what Port in the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> Consigned, and the Names of the persons Signing the Certificates, of the Landing the same in <hi>England,</hi> and the date of the said Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, and where the same are or were Laden, and also of the Qualities and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:184548:39"/> Quantities, Marks and Numbers contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the said Certificates, in order that the same may be compared with the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred Account, appointed by this Act to be kept by the Commissioners or Farmers of the Customs of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And for preventing the mischief of Razing, Obliterating or Interlining such Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates,<note place="margin">Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates on Paper.</note> as aforesaid, Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all such Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates shall be written upon Paper and not Parchment, and that the Quantities and Qualities, Marks and Numbers therein exprest, shall not be Obliterated or Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lined, upon any pretence whatsoever.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Ports of Export and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</note> That all such Goods, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, as shall from time to time be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported from the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> into the Ports of this Kingdom, or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Wales,</hi> in manner as aforesaid, shall be Shipped off, and Entred at the Ports of <hi>Dublin, Waterford, Youghall, Kingsale, Cork</hi> and <hi>Drogheda,</hi> in the said Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and at or from no other Port or Place within the said Kingdom; nor shall the same be Imported into any parts of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Wales,</hi> other than the Ports of <hi>Biddiford, Barnstable, Minhead, Bridgwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Bristol, Milford Haven, Chester</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verpool;</hi> Any thing in this Act to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And to the intent and purpose that this Act may more effectually be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for preventing the growing mischiefs that daily do or may arise to this Kingdom, from the Exportation of such Goods, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, or any of them out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> should the same still be
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:184548:39"/> suffered to be sent from thence to supply the Foreign Markets, that are or have been supplied from <hi>England,</hi> Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this Act For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Office and 500 <hi>l.</hi>
               </note> That if any Commissioner or Commissioners, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer or Farmers of the Revenue of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or Officer or Officers Imployed under them in the Management of the said Revenue there, shall from and after the said Four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> take, or suffer to be taken any Entry outward, or sign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cocket, Warrant or Sufferance, for the Shipping and Exporting any such Goods, as aforesaid, into any Kingdom, State or Dominion whatsoever (except as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said) or shall wittingly or willingly permit, contrive or suffer the same to be done, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly, contrary to the true intent and meaning of this Act, That then, and in every such case, such Commission<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or Commissioners, Farmer or Farmers, Officer or Officers, so offending in the Signing such Cocket, Warrant or Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for the Shipping or Exporting any of the said Goods into any other Kingdom, State or Dominion or Place whatsoever (except as aforesaid) or passing such en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for the same, or any wise conniving thereat, contrary to the true intent and meaning hereof, or shall otherwise fail or neglect to perform all other Duties requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by this present Act, shall, for every such Offence or neglect, Forfeit his Office, and shall moreover for every such Offence, Forfeit the sum of Five hundred pounds, to be recovered and imployed in manner and form as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Where Offences shall be Tried.</note> That every Offence which shall be done or committed, contrary to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:184548:40"/> this Act, shall and may be Inquired of, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Heard and Determined in the County where any such Goods, as aforesaid, shall be so Laden or put on Board, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, or else in the County, either in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> where such Offender shall happen to be Apprehended or Arrested for such Offence, or where any such of the Goods aforesaid, or the said Ship or Ships, Vessels, Hulks, Barks or Boats shall happen to be Seized or Taken or Brought in, and that the said Tryal shall be in such manner and form, and in such effect to all intents and purposes, as if the same Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence had been wholly done and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the same County.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Persons Sued, how to Plead.</note> That if any Action, Bill, Plaint, Suit or Information shall be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced or Prosecuted against any person, for what he shall do in pursuance of this Act, such person so Sued, shall and may File a Common Bail, or enter into a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon appearance and plead the general Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue not Guilty, and upon Issue joyned, may give this Act, and the special matter in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and if the Plaintiff or Prosecutor shall become nonsuit, or suffer disconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, or if a Verdict pass against him, or if upon Demurrer, Judgment pass against him, the Defendant shall recover Treble Costs and Damages for the Molestation.</p>
            <p>And for the further Incouragement of the Woollen Manufactures of <hi>England,</hi> Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">How Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> shall be Import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>Ireland,</hi> into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> That it shall and may be Lawful, from and after the said Four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> to Import from the said Ports of <hi>Doublin, Waterford, Youghall, Kingsale, Cork</hi> and <hi>Drogheda,</hi> in the Kingdom of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:184548:40"/>
               <hi>Ireland,</hi> any Wooll, Wooll-fells, Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Mortlings, Wooll-flocks, Worsted, Bay, or Woollen Yarn, Cloth, Serges, Bays, Kerseys, Frizes, Druggets, Shalloons, Stuffs, Cloth-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or any other Drapery made of or mixed with Wooll, or Wooll-flocks, and Manufactured in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> into such Ports of this Kingdom or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Wales</hi> only, as aforesaid, so as No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice be first given to the Commissioners, or Chief Managers of His Majesties Customs in this Kingdom, or to the Chief Customer or Collector, in the Port to which the same is intended to be Brought, of the Quantity, Quality and Package, together with the Marks and Numbers thereof, with the Name of the Ship and Master or Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, on which the said Goods are to be La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and the Place or Port into which they are intended to be Imported, and so as Bond be first entred into, to the Use of His Majesty, His Heirs and Successors, with one or more sufficient Sureties; in Treble the Value of the Goods so intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Imported, That the same shall (the Dangers of the Seas excepted) be Landed accordingly, and so as a Licence be also first taken, under the hands of the Commissioners, or Chief Managers of the Customs for the time being, or Three of them, or from the Chief Customer or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector where such Bond is given, for the Landing and Importing thereof as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said; which Licence they are hereby Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized and Required to Grant, without any see or Reward, or any other Charge, to the person demanding the same, any Law, Statute, or Usage to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:184548:41"/>
            <p>And for the more effectual preventing the Transportation of Wooll, Wooll-fells, Shortlings, Mortlings or Wooll-flocks, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, Bay, or Woollen Yarn, or any Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of Wooll or Wooll-flocks, or mixed with the same, into Foreign parts; Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That the Penalties and Forfeitures of the Bonds,<note place="margin">Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Bonds not Assigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> which by this Act or any other former Law or Usage are to be given, or have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for any Wooll, or any of the Commodities afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, intended to be Exported from that Kingdom, to be brought into the Ports of this Kingdom, or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> as aforesaid, shall not, on any Consideration whatsoever, be Granted or Assigned over to any person whatsoever; And that all such Grants and Assignments are and shall be void to all intents and purposes; Any Law, Usage or Statute to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty shall appoint Cruizers to seize all Ships ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Wooll.</note>And for the better preventing the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Wooll out of this Kingdom or <hi>Ireland,</hi> into Foreign Parts, Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That the Lord High Admiral of <hi>England,</hi> or Commission<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for executing the Office of High Admiral for the time being, shall direct and appoint two Ships of the Fifth Rate, and two Ships of the Sixth Rate, and eight Armed Sloops, constantly to Cruize on the Coasts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly between the North of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with Orders to Take and Seize all Ships, Vessels and Boats which shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port any Wooll, with intent to carry it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Foreign parts; And that the Lord High Admiral, or Commissioners, as aforesaid, shall send a List of all such Ships and Sloops,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:184548:41"/> and the Names of the Commanders, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with true Copies of their several In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions that are or shall be given, to the Commissioners of the Customs in <hi>London,</hi> within Ten days after such Orders, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, are or shall be given.</p>
            <p>And for the Incouragement of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and Mariners belonging to the Ships and Sloops aforesaid,<note place="margin">Wooll, Ships, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Seized, to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and Sold by Inch of Candle.</note> Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all Wooll, Ships, Vessels or Boats that shall be so Seized or Taken, shall be Forfeited, and all such Wooll shall be Lodged in the Kings Ware-house in such Port where it is or shall be Taken or Seized, or into which it shall be brought, until it shall be Condemned according to Law; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so Condemned, shall be exposed pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly to Sale, after One and twenty days, publick notice being given in Writing at the Custom-house of the said Port, and on the Royal Exchange of <hi>London,</hi> by Inch of Candle, to the last and best Bidder;<note place="margin">How to be Disposed of.</note> And all Ships, Vessels or Boats that shall be so Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and Condemned, as aforesaid, shall, together with all their Guns, Tackle, Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture and Apparel, be exposed to Sale in like manner; And that one fourth part of the Produce of the Wooll, Ships, Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels and Boats so Sold, as aforesaid, shall be to the Commander, one other Fourth part to the Officers of the Ship or Ships, Sloop or Sloops that took the same, one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fourth part to the Mariners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to such Ship, Vessel or Sloop, to be equally divided and paid amongst the said Mariners by the Collectors of the said Port, or such person or persons as shall be Authorized to pay the same, and the other Fourth part thereof to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:184548:42"/> His Heirs and Successors, after a dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction made out of the last Fourth part of all the Charges of Prosecution and Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>And for preventing of all Composition or Confederacy by any Commander of any Ship,<note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander Offending Forfeits all his Pay, Suffers six Months Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated.</note> Vessel or Sloop, with any person whatsoever concerned in such Wooll or Ship, Vessel or Boat, as aforesaid, Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That every Commander of such Ship or Sloop, neglecting his Duty by this Act Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, or Compounding for any Wooll, Ship, Vessel or Boat, as aforesaid, or Conniving at the Exportation of any Wooll, shall Lose and Forfeit all Pay and Wages due to him or them, and suffer Six Months Imprisonment, and be for ever incapable of Serving His Majesty in any Office in the Navy.</p>
            <p>And for the more effectual Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Woollen Manufacture of this Kingdom,<note place="margin">After 1 <hi>Decem.</hi> 1699. Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the <hi>English</hi> Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not to be laid on Board any Ship on any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</note> Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That from and after the First day of <hi>December,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hundred nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine, no Wooll, Wooll-fells, Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Mortlings, Wooll-flocks, Worsted, Bay, or Woollen Yarn, Cloth, Serge, Bays, Kerseys, Says, Frizes, Druggets, Cloth-Serges, Shalloons or any other Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery Stuffs or Woollen Manufactures whatsoever, made or mixt with Wooll or Wooll-flocks, being of the Product or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture of any of the <hi>English</hi> Plantations in <hi>America,</hi> shall be loaden or laid on Board in any Ship or Vessel, in any Place or Parts within any of the said <hi>English</hi> Plantations, upon any pretence whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; As likewise that no such Wooll, Wooll-fells,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:184548:42"/> Shortlings, Mortlings, Wooll-flocks, Worsted, Bay, or Woollen Yarn, Cloth,<note place="margin">Nor to be Loaden on any Horse, Cart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported out of the said Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to any other place whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</note> Serge, Bays, Kerseys, Says, Frizes, Drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets, Cloth Serges, Shalloons or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Drapery Stuffs, or Woollen Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures whatsoever, made up or mixt with Wooll or Wooll-flocks, being of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct or Manufacture of any of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Plantations in <hi>America,</hi> as aforesaid, shall be Loaden upon any Horse, Cart or other Carriage, to the intent and purpose to be Exported, Transported, Carried or Conveyed out of the said <hi>English</hi> Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to any other of the said Plantations, or to any other Place whatsoever, upon the same and like Pains,<note place="margin">The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> Penalties and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, to and upon all and every the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender and Offenders herein, within all and every of the said <hi>English</hi> Plantations respectively, as are prescribed and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by this Act for the like Offences Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted within the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> And all Governors or Commanders in Chief of the said respective Plantations,<note place="margin">Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to put this Act in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> as also all Officers Imployed in the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms, or other Branches of His Majesties Revenue there, are hereby Authorized, Charged and Required to take effectual care, That the true intent and meaning of this Act, so far forth as it relates to the said respective Plantations, be duly put in Execution.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity aforesaid,<note place="margin">Persons Offending against this Act how to be prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> That all and every person and persons, who after the said Four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> shall be guilty of any Offence or Offences, contrary to the true intent and meaning of this or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Act of Parliament made for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the Exportation of Wooll, shall
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:184548:43"/> and may be Prosecuted for any such Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or Offences by Action, Suit or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in any of His Majesties Courts of Record at <hi>Westminster,</hi> and thereupon a <hi>Capias</hi> shall and may Issue the first Process, specifying the Sum of the Penalty Sued for; and such person or persons shall be obliged to give good and sufficient Bail and Security, by Natural Born Subjects or Denizens, to the Officer Serving or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting such Process against him or them, to Appear in the Court out of which such <hi>Capias</hi> shall Issue, at the day of the Return of such Writ, to answer such Suit or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution, and shall likewise at the time of such Appearance, give sufficient Bail or Security by such persons, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, in the said Court, to answer and pay the Forfeitures and Penalties In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred for such Offence or Offences, in case he, she or they shall be Convict there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or to yield his, her or their Bodies to Prison.</p>
            <p>Provided also, and it is hereby further Enacted, That after the Nine and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>September,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hundred nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine, the Lord Lieutenant, Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty, or Lords Justices for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ireland.</note> or any of them, are hereby Required to give Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in Council, that this Act shall be given in Charge by the several Judges of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> at all the Assizes that shall be held in that Kingdom, to the end that this Act may be strictly put in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, according to the true intent and meaning thereof; Which said Judges are hereby Impowered and Required, from time to time, to take particular Accounts
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:184548:43"/> throughout their respective Circuits, of the due Execution of this Act, and at their Returns to <hi>Dublin,</hi> at the end of every Circuit, shall Acquaint the said Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, Lord Deputy, or Lords Justices of that Kingdom for the time being in Council, with all Accounts or Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they shall have so Received of any Breach of the said Act, or Negligence or Faults in any of the Officers, to whom the Execution of this Act is Committed, to the end that the said Chief Governors, or any of them, for the time being, may be the better Informed and Inabled to Look to and Provide for the strict and punctual observation of this Act, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that Kingdom; Of which the said Chief Governors, or any of them, for the time being, shall once every year, lay a particular Account in Writing, under his or their Hands, before the King, His Heirs and Successors in Council.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:44"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:44"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:45"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:45"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:46"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:46"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:47"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184548:47"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>